Guide to the Sidney Dean Townley Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Sidney Dean Townley papers
circa 1827-1939
SC0273
Townley, Sidney Dean, 1867-1946.
7.5 Linear feet
Personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts, research notes including astronomical observations and geological measurements, articles, lectures, personal diaries, family genealogy, and a collection of family photographs including glass plate negatives and a glass plate negative format camera.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Astronomer. Studied at Lick Observatory on Mount Hamilton, California, and at the Universities of Berlin and Munich. Before becoming a Professor of Applied Mathematics at Stanford Unviersiy in 1907, Townley taught at U.C. Berkeley and was Astronomer at the International Latitude Observatory in Ukiah, California. He became Professor Emeritus of Astronomy and Geodesy at Stanford in 1932. In addition to practical astronomy, his research interests included asteroids, comets and variable stars, latitude measurements, and seismology.
Description of the Collection
Personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts, research notes including astronomical observations and geological measurements, articles, lectures, personal diaries, family genealogy, and a collection of family photographs including glass plate negatives and a glass plate negative format camera.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Mathematics. Faculty.; Townley, Sidney Dean, 1867-1946.; Astronomy.; Diaries.; Geodesy.; Glass plate negatives.; Latitude variation.; Photoprints.; Seismology.; Social history--19th century.; Social history--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Papers, 1886-1939
  - Articles and Lectures
    - Address of the Reitiring President of the Society in Awarding the Bruce Gold Medal to Mr. Edward Emerson Barnard, 1917 April; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Automobile Routes from California to the Path of Totality for the Solar Eclipse of June 8, 1918, 1918 April; Reprint and clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Branner, John Casper, Undated; Typescript (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Comstock, George Gary, 1934 August; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Contribution of Astronomy to Practical Religion and the Broader Aspects of Human Welfare, Undated; Typescript (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diary of a Student of the University of Wisconsin, 1886-1892; Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Earthquakes - the California Earthquake of 1906 with special reference to the Earth displacements, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Earthquakes - Earthquakes felt in San Francisco from January 1, 1907 to December 10, 1931, of intensity III or greater, Undated; Typescript (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Earthquakes - Earthquakes of the Pacific Coast of the United States, 1919 September; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Earthquakes - Earthquakes and Variations in Latitude, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Earthquakes - Report on Certain Earthquakes in California, as affecting insurance, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Earthquakes - the San Jacinto Earthquake of April 21, 1918, 1918 September; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Eclipse Stations in Oregon and Washington, 1918 February; Reprint (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Excursion to La Honda and Moss Beach, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Halley's Comet, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Light Curve of Nova Persei, 1901, Undated; Typescript (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Light of All the Stars, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Measurement of Celestial Distances, Undated; Typescript (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Other Worlds Than Ours, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Palo Alto Union High School, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Probability of Collisions Among the Stars, Undated; Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Reform of the Calendar, Undated; Notes and reference studies (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Resultate des Internationalen Breitendienstes, 1907 June; Reprint (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Shifting of the Earth's Axis, 1909 November; Reprint (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Solar Eclipses, Undated; Lecture (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Some Problems of Astronomy, Undated; Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Some Remarks on Dr. Lawson's paper, Undated; Typescript (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Sun's Heat, Undated; Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Variable Stars, Undated; Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Variable Stars - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Variable Stars (Notes on Variable Stars Catalog), Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Variation of Latitude, Undated; Lecture (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Calculations
    - Altitude and Azimuth of the Sun, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Latitudel Hot Springs, Nevada, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conferences
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, Pacific Division - Committee on Arrangements, 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - AAAS - Programs and Meeting Announcements, 1921-1936 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - AAAS - Preliminary Announcements, 1921-1926 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Pacific Science Congress, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous material
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Personal - Clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Physical Sciences, School of, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Primary and Grammar School, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Student Reports - Astronomy 165, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - University of Chicago, Quarter System, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Additional Papers, 1827-1934; Accession ARCH-1986-049
  - Correspondence - Automobiles, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - family, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Prairie Home Cemetery, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Astronomy (manuscript): p. 1-98, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Astronomy (manuscript): p. 99-128, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Astronomy (manuscript): p. 129-306, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Planters Almanac, vols. 1898-1902 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Resolution, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Family genealogy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Wright and Townley Genealogies by Lucille Townley Clark, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pitkin Family of America: A genealogy of the Descendents of William Pitkin by A.P. Pitkin, 1827 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1903-1904 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1905-1906 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1907-1908 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1911-1912 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1913-1914 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1917-1918 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1921-1922 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1923-1924 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1925-1926 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Townley, S.D.: Diaries, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Townley, S.D.: Honeymoon diary and photo record (2 vol.), 1894; Inventory for glass negatives included in collection (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Memoirs/Essays, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - family, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs - family, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal ephemera, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Senior Contest Oration, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Memory Book (S.D. Townley's mother? -- Isabel), Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - S.D. Townley birthday book, Undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Family - baby toys, Undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Townley, Francis Wright - correspondence, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Townley, Francis Wright - correspondence, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Townley, Francis Wright - correspondence, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Wright, Francis: Diary, 1895 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Wright family photo album, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Townley, Francis Wright memory book, 1888 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Townley, Francis Wright - textbooks - Mills College, 1888 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Townley, Francis Wright - miscellaneous, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Townley, Sidney: Diary, 1885-1897; Also includes Photograph of University of Wisconsin baseball team (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Astronomical file cards - Catalogued observations, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Astronomical file cards - Catalogued observations, Undated (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, professional, 1929-1932 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, professional, 1929-1934 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Lick Observatory Notebook, Number 1, 1892 August 19-December 10 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Lick Observatory Notebook, Number 2, 1892 January 2- (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Lick Observatory Notebook, "Variable Stars", 1902 May 22-July 12 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Glass Plate Negative Collection, Undated; Accession ARCH-1986-049
  Sidney D. Townley's Glass plate camera and Tripod (stored in original case). Glass negs (inventory available in manuscript collection Box 7 folder 3)
  - 5 x 7" Glass Negatives #1-108, Undated (Box 1)
  - 5 x 7" Glass Negatives #109-204, Undated (Box 2)
  - 5 x 7" Glass Negatives #204-307, Undated (Box 3)
  - 5 x 7" Glass Negatives #308-390, Undated (Box 4)
  - 4 x 5" Glass Negatives #326-335; 4 x 5" Glass negatives "Babies" #244, 245, 248, 263, 265, 270, 271, 289, 274; 3 x 4" Lantern slides; 20 5 x 7" Glass negatives - separate, Undated (Box 5)